Finding Aid for Lucius L. Hubbard Papers, 1871-1935
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Lucius L. Hubbard papers
1871-1935
Hubbard, Lucius L. (Lucius Lee), 1849-1933.
851638 Aa 2 Ac
State Geologist and University of Michigan Regent. Personal and business correspondence and letter books concerning personal matters, his literary and book collecting interests, geology and mining in Michigan, the publication of his writings, and University of Michigan affairs.
5 linear feet
1 oversize folders
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Charlotte Hubbard Goodell (donor 1360 ) and came to the library in 1941.
The collection is open to research.
Lucius Lee Hubbard was born in Cincinnati, Ohio on August 7, 1849. He received his AB from Harvard in 1872 and his LL.B from Boston University in 1875. After receiving his law degree he took up practice in Boston only to give it up a few years later to devote himself to a career in science. In 1886, he took the AM and Ph.D. degrees from the University of Bonn where he worked with Von Laseaulz. From 1891 to 1893, Hubbard served as assistant to M. E. Wadsworth with the State Geological Survey of Michigan based in Houghton, and then from 1893 to 1899 as Michigan state geologist.
Hubbard was instrumental in the development the state mining industry, most notably in the area of Houghton. After leaving the geological survey, he then became general manager of the Copper Range Mining Co. and the Champion Copper Co., and afterwards was president of the Ojibway Mining Co. From 1905 to 1917 he was a member of the board of control of the Michigan College of Mines. In addition, he was a member of the board of scientific advisers of the geological survey and director of the Houghton National Bank and director and president of the South Range Bank. Houghton served as Regent of the University of Michigan from 1911 until his death in 1933.
Hubbard was author of books on mineralogy and geology, and a collector of Gulliver's Travels and Robinson Crusoe books. He died in Eagle Harbor, Michigan, August 3, 1933.
The Hubbard papers relate to his career as a geologist, to his service as a member of the University of Michigan Board of Regents, and to his other various literary and scientific interests. The collection has been arranged into four series: Correspondence; University of Michigan papers; Other Activities (mining and geological interests); and bound personal and business records.
Subjects:
Champion Copper Company.; Copper Range Company.; Geology--Michigan.; Harvard University.; Houghton (Mich.); Houghton Copper Company.; Hubbard, Lucius L. (Lucius Lee), 1849-1933.; Indians of North America--Michigan.; Isle Royale (Mich.); Maine.; Mayflower Mining Company.; Mines and mineral resources--Michigan.; Moosehead Lake (Me.); St. Mary's Canal Mineral Land Company.; University of Michigan. Board of Regents.; University of Michigan--History.History.; Geology--Maine.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Copper.; Hubbard, Lucius L. (Lucius Lee), 1849-1933.; Maine.
Contributors:
Adams, Randolph Greenfield, 1892-1951.; Allen, Rolland Craten, 1881-1948.; Bates, Henry Moore, 1869-1949.; Beal, Junius E. (Junius Emery), 1860-1942.; Bishop, William Warner, 1871-1955.; Bliss, Aaron Thomas, 1837-1906.; Bulkley, Harry C. (Harry Conant), b. 1870.; Burrows, Julius C. (Julius Caesar), 1837-1915.; Bursley, Joseph Aldrich, 1877-1950.; Burton, Marion Le Roy, 1874-1925.; Clements, William L. (William Lawrence), 1861-1934.; Comstock, William Alfred, 1877-1949.; Cooley, Mortimer E. (Mortimer Elwyn), 1855-1944.; Curtiss, Ralph Hamilton, 1880-1929.; Davis, Charles Albert, b. 1861.; Demmon, Isaac Newton, 1842-1920.; Ferris, Woodbridge N., 1853-1928.; Fordney, Joseph W. (Joseph Warren), 1853-1932.; Gore, Victor M.; Green, Fred W. (Fred Warren), 1872-1936.; Hanchett, Benjamin Sawtell, 1868-1933.; Hinsdale, W. B. (Wilbert B.), 1851-1944.; Hobbs, William Herbert, 1864-1952.; Houghton, Jacob, 1827-1903.; Hutchins, Harry B. (Harry Burns), 1847-1930.; Kelsey, Francis W. (Francis Willey), b. 1858.; Knox, Frank, 1874-1944.; Koch, Theodore Wesley, 1871-1941.; Kraus, Edward Henry, 1875-1973; Lane, Alfred C. (Alfred Church), b. 1863.; Little, Clarence C. (Clarence Cook), b. 1888.; Martindale, Frederick C.; Murfin, James Orin, 1875-1940.; Osborn, Chase S. (Chase Salmon), b. 1860.; Pinchot, Gifford, 1865-1946.; Rich, John Treadway, 1841-1926.; Roosevelt, Franklin D. (Franklin Delano), 1882-1945.; Roth, Filibert, 1858-1925.; Russell, Israel C. (Israel Cook), 1852-1906.; Ruthven, Alexander Grant, 1882-1971.; Sawyer, Walter H. (Walter Hulme), 1861-1931.; Sleeper, Albert E., 1862-1934.; Smith, John Walter, 1845-1925.; Smith, Shirley Wheeler, 1875-1959.; Smith, William Alden, 1859-1932.; Stone, Ralph, 1868-1956.; Townsend, Charles E. (Charles Elroy), 1856-1924.; Vandenberg, Arthur H. (Arthur Hendrick), 1884-1951.; Wadsworth, M. Edward (Marshman Edward), 1847-1921.; Warner, Frederick Maltby, 1865-1923.; White, Peter, 1830-1908.; Young, Horace Olin, 1850-1917.
Genre Terms:
Diaries.; Photographs.; Prints.
- Correspondence
  The correspondence series dates from 1871 to 1935 and relates to his career as state geologist, a member of the University of Michigan Board of Regents, his business career, and his literary interests. His correspondents include Rolland C. Allen, Henry M. Bates, Junius E. Beal, William W. Bishop, Aaron T. Bliss, Julius C. Burrows, Marion L. Burton, William L. Clements, Mortimer E. Cooley, Charles A. Davis, Woodbridge N. Ferris, Fred W. Green, William H. Hobbs, Jacob Houghton, Harry B. Hutchins, Francis W. Kelsey, Frank Knox, Theodore W. Koch, Edward H. Kraus, Alfred C. Lane, Clarence C. Little, James O. Murfin, Chase S. Osborn, Gifford Pinchot, John T. Rich, Filibert Roth, Israel C. Russell, Alexander G. Ruthven, Walter H. Sawyer, Albert E. Sleeper, Shirley W. Smith, William A. Smith, Ralph Stone, Marshman E. Wadsworth, Fred M. Warner, Peter Q. White, and H. Olin Young. A card file index to Hubbard's correspondents is available in the Reading Room of the library.
  - 1871-1911 (Box 1)
  - 1912-1928 (Box 2)
  - 1929-1935, undated; 11 folders (Box 3, Folder 1-11)
  - Fragmentary (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Personal family correspondence (Box 3, Folder 12a)
- University of Michigan
  The University of Michigan series documents Hubbard's service as Regents and his involvement in issues confronting the University. Included in this series are reports, memoranda and proposals, petitions directed to the Board of Regents, and various news articles of interest to him as a Regent.
  - Reports about finances, budgets, and endowments (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Article from the Saginaw News Courier about President Burton, December 28, 1924 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Poems-In Memoriam of Marion LeRoy Burton
  - Proposal for the establishment of research committees in the Department of Engineering Research, April 22, 1929 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Memorandum to the faculties of the Colleges of Engineering and Architecture about the length of the curricula
  - Statement for the regents about a forest experiment station (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Memoranda for a report on a biological station
  - Articles about the date of founding of the University (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Report to the Board of Regents on the Halsey collection of rare books submitted by Isaac N. Demmon, 1915 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Report of committee on presidential nominations on interview with President Harry Woodburn Chase of North Carolina University
  - Report about need for more dormitories
  - Report of a Dean's Meeting to discuss building new dormitories, December, 1928 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Extracts from the Articles of Association of the University of Michigan League Building Association
  - Copy of The UBS Weekly Bulletin of containing an article about regents who visited Douglas Lake, July 22, 1911 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Report of the Graduate Schools of the American Universities, October, 1911
  - Report about the club house of the University Club of Ann Arbor, February 15, 1913
  - Report about the constitution of the Division of Hygiene and Public Health
  - Minutes of the Committee of Five on a Comprehensive Building Program (Incomplete), February 28, 1924 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Report on University science program
  - Count of the enrollment, September 24, 1925
  - Directions to those who are to take a trip to the "Comet Halley"
  - Petition to the Board of Regents from the U. of M. Club of New York that Fielding H. Yost be head of the Department of Physical Education (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Article saying the proper title of the chief executive officer of the University should be Chancellor
  - Excerpts from the records of the Regents about Rev. George P. Williams
  - Copies of resolutions and by-laws of the Regents (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Petition to the Regents by Charles H. D. Myers for his long-deferred diploma (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Copy of an act of the 55th Legislature of the State of Michigan to empower the Board of Regents to contract for sewage, light, water or other facilities, 1929
  - An article about Laurence Binyon, an English author
  - Miscellaneous notes by Hubbard about the University (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - An Address by Arthur H. Vandenberg of Grand Rapids, at the dinner of the University Press Club of Michigan, October 30, 1925 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Statistics of the General Library, University of Michigan, March, 1913-September, 1914 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    (Not every month included)
  - Lists of books added to the University Library
    - 1896 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - November 1-16, 1912
    - April 16-30, 1913
    - May 16-31, 1913
    - July 16-August 30, 1913
    - September, 1913
    - October 1-13, 1913
    - January 15, 1914
  - Lists of Engineering duplicate books and periodicals for exchange, University of Michigan, June, 1913 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Circulation report of the General Library, 1912-1913
  - Reports of the Accessions Department of the University Library
    - 1911-1912
    - July 1, 1912-June 30, 1913
  - List of Spanish books (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Memoranda of business transacted at meetings of the Library Committee
    - November 11, 1912
    - April 22, 1913
    - January 13, 1914
  - The published voyages of William Dampier
  - List of antiques for sale at an auction, December 14, 1880
  - Acknowledgments of books and other gifts which Hubbard has donated to various libraries (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Statements from booksellers, 1879-1915 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Miscellaneous notes about books which Hubbard has read (Box 3, Folder 33)
- Other Activities (including mining and geological interests)
  The other activities series documents his service as state geologist and his interest in the development of Michigan's mineral resources. Included are reports, notes, maps, articles and field notebooks. A portion of this series concerns his interest in the state of Maine, particularly Moosehead Lake.
  - Inaugural address of L. L. Hubbard, of Cincinnati, Ohio, delivered before the "Golden Branch" of Phillip's Exeter Academy, April 18, 1868 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Separat-Abdruck aus den Sitzungsberichten der niederrhienischen Gesellschaft für Natur-und Heilkunde. Sitzung am 7. Juni, 1886
  - Speech given to graduating class, not identified, undated
  - Unidentified speech
  - Notes of the Michigan Geological Survey, Ontonagon Road (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Reports and notes of the U S Geological Survey (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Annual reports of the State Geologist
    - January 1, 1895 (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - January 1, 1896
    - December 15, 1896
    - January 1, 1898
    - January 2, 1899
  - Minutes of a meeting of the Board of Scientific Advisers
    - April 8, 1910 (Box 3, Folder 38)
    - December 23, 1910
    - December 16, 1911
    - December 13, 1913
  - The geological aspects of the copper range lands, 1899; 1900 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Notes on chlorastrolite, undated
  - Miscellaneous notes about mines and geology (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Progress reports of Longyear and Hodge, Mining Engineers, September 1909-January 1911 (Box 3, Folder 41-45)
  - Maps
    - Map of Moosehead Lake, 1st edition, 1879; 4 copies (Box 3, Folder 46)
    - Map of Moosehead Lake, 2nd edition, 1899
    - Map of Moosehead Lake, 5th edition, 1893; 2 copies
    - Map of Moosehead and Upper Lake region of Maine (Box 3, Folder 47)
    - Hubbard's Lumbermen's and Tourist's Map of Northern Maine, 1894; 3 copies (Box 3, Folder 48)
    - Hubbard's Lumbermen's and Tourist's Map of Northern Maine, 1879-1929
    - Map of Moosehead Lake, Maine (Box 3, Folder 49)
    - Maps of the State of Maine, 2 folders (Box 3, Folder 50-51)
    - Miscellaneous maps, often not identified (Box 3, Folder 52)
    - Miscellaneous manuscript maps, often not identified, 5 folders (Box 3, Folder 53-57)
    - A Bibliography of the Maps of Maine," by Edgar Crosby Smith, 1903 (Box 3, Folder 58)
    - Offers sent to Hubbard to purchase maps, and other note about written by Hubbard (Box 3, Folder 59)
  - Report on the Seneca Mine, about, 1920 (Box 4, Folder 60)
  - Reports and notes of the Seneca Copper Corporation, 1920-1921; undated; 2 folders (Box 4, Folder 61-62)
  - Reports and notes of the St. Mary's Canal Mineral Land Co., 1903-1904 (Box 4, Folder 63)
    (Later the Houghton Copper Company)
  - Reports and notes of the Houghton Copper Company, 1910-1913; undated; 3 folders (Box 4, Folder 64-66)
  - Reports and notes of the Champion Copper Company, 1900-1905; 1923 undated; 5 folders (Box 4, Folder 67-71)
  - General reports of the Copper Range Co., 1899-1903 (Box 4, Folder 72-73)
  - Typewritten descriptions of sections of Michigan rocks (Box 4, Folder 74)
  - Chart showing the cost of production of the Atlantic Mine, 1900-1906
  - Chart showing the cost of production of the Mohawk Mine, 1903-1907
  - Notes on the Central Mine, Keweenaw Co., March, 1895 (Box 4, Folder 75)
  - Reports of the Mayflower Mining Company, May, 1899 (Box 4, Folder 76)
  - Reports and notes of the South Lake Mining Co., 1909-1910; undated (Box 4, Folder 77)
  - Data and prospects on copper mining lands in the Ontonagon District, Michigan, August 1915 (Box 4, Folder 78)
  - Notes on Ojibway Mining Company
  - Report of the Nevada Consolidated Copper Company (Box 4, Folder 79)
  - Report on the Bluestone Mine, Lyons Co., Nevada
    - August 3, 1905
    - January 19, 1906
  - Report on Trimountain Co., February 6, 1899 (Box 4, Folder 80)
  - Report on the Shelden and Columbian property, May 1899
  - Articles about Lake Superior copper
    (about 1897)
    - January 13 circa 1897 (Box 4, Folder 81)
    - January 23 circa 1897
    - April 4 circa 1897
    - May 31 circa 1897
  - Affidavit of Lucius L. Hubbard for the Champion Copper case, May 1, 1923 (Box 4, Folder 82)
    (Original and revised copies)
  - Supplemental statement of L. L. Hubbard of an affidavit of, May, 1923
  - Four blueprints of the Champion Copper Co. (Box 4, Folder 83)
  - Three blueprints of the Seneca Copper Co. (Box 4, Folder 84)
  - Map for the South Lake Mining Co., by Hubbard, 1912 (Box 4, Folder 85)
  - Assay of manganese ore from Copper Harbor (Box 4, Folder 86)
  - Notes about the Michigan collection of mines
  - Notes about rock shipped from, January 1-September, 1920
  - Correlation of the Keweenaw series at Isle Royale, Copper Falls and Eagle River, October 20, 1894
  - Assignment of work by Dr. Hubbard in 1891 or 1892 concerning the microscopic character of rocks (Box 4, Folder 87)
  - Notes about Mt. Kineo (Box 4, Folder 87)
  - Preliminary notes on slides, etc., in the Keweenaw series on Keweenaw Point, March, 1896 (Box 4, Folder 88)
  - Diagrams of the Copper Range Co. and the Kearsarge Lode, Michigan (Box 4, Folder 89)
  - Suggestions for methods in field work, about, 1895 (Box 4, Folder 90)
  - The Winning of Native Copper, undated (Box 4, Folder 91)
  - Estimate of width of lode sent to stamp mill in, 1904 (Box 4, Folder 92)
  - Comparison of leading mines in production and cost, 1904
  - Schedule for capitalized development of underground mines
  - Article about the influence of the topography of foot wall beds upon the subsequent deposition and distribution of copper in overlying beds (Box 4, Folder 93)
  - Article about foot wall shafts in Lake Superior copper mines
  - Article about copper deposits
  - Suggestions as to working the mining claims in the Leadville Mining District, undated (Box 4, Folder 94)
  - Notes on Copper Falls
  - Article about the rock beds between Keweenaw Point and Isle Royale
  - Photostat copies of articles about copper, no author or dates (Box 4, Folder 95)
  - Report on exploratory work of on Isle Royale, Michigan, 1899 (Box 4, Folder 96)
  - Notations on forest taxation (Box 4, Folder 97)
  - Blanks filled in by Hubbard of the Board of State Tax Commissioners, Houghton, Michigan, as of, April 1, 1911
  - Watercolor painting on a greeting card sent by Emil Lorch, 1921 (Box 4, Folder 98)
  - Photostatic copies (in German) of information and pictures concerning abnormal developments of the human (Box 4, Folder 99)
  - An article "A Sketch of the Old Spanish Mines," by Joseph Oliver (Box 4, Folder 100)
  - Articles of Association of the Keweenaw Club of Houghton, Michigan (Box 4, Folder 101)
  - Paper about organizing the Portage Lake Whist Club
  - Rules for the Onigaming Yacht Club Regatta, October 9, 1897
  - Indian names with translation into English (Box 4, Folder 102)
  - U.S. Field Notes (Box 4, Folder 103)
    (four sets, one for Houghton County and another dated around 1900 otherwise unidentified)
  - Two small field notebooks of Hubbard, one dating around 1899-1900 the other around 1901-1902 (Box 4, Folder 104)
  - Notes about corporations (Box 4, Folder 105)
  - Lecture notes on lithology, March, 1893
  - Certificate of election to the Phi Beta Kappa, April 2, 1892 (Box 4, Folder 106)
  - Certificate of election to St. Paul's Religious Society in Harvard College, January 17, 1872
  - Certificate of membership in the American Defense Society, May, 1916
  - Certificate from the Secretary of State, Daniel E. Soper, saying that the Articles of Association of the Keweenaw Club of Houghton were recorded in his office, August 24, 1891
  - Warrant saying that Hubbard is a hospital steward, February 11, 1879
  - Receipt of payment of $20.10 by L. L. Hubbard to the Young's Hotel in Boston, April 20, 1923 (Box 4, Folder 107)
  - Receipt of payment of a freight bill to the Copper Range Railroad Co., November 26, 1909
  - Petition to the residents of Portage Township to abolish houses of prostitution in the area (Box 4, Folder 108)
  - Newspaper articles
    - "Camping Out" (Box 4, Folder 109)
    - "Over 200 Miles by Canoe"
    - "Summer Resorts of Maine,", April 29, 1882
    - "A Few Days Fishing,", October 7, 1879
  - Declaration and notice of rule to plead in the Circuit Court of the County of Houghton, between Charles T. Davis and Lucius Lee Hubbard and Frances J. Hubbard (Box 4, Folder 110)
  - Brief for the plaintiff in error; Lucius L. Hubbard, Plaintiff in Error vs. The New York, New England and Western Investment Co. (Box 4, Folder 111)
  - Agreement Of L. L. Hubbard, H. B. Patton, A. C. Lane, and F. F. Sharpless, pledging amounts of money to buy a house and land in Houghton (Box 4, Folder 112)
  - Option of land in Keweenaw County given to Hubbard
  - Agreements and options to buy land, given to Hubbard, 1906 (Box 4, Folder 113)
  - "A Catalogue of the Officers and Students of Harvard Univ., for the Academical Year, 1869-1870" (Box 4, Folder 114)
  - Extract from Tufts College Studies, "Wet and Dry Differentiation of Igneous Rocks," by A. C. Lane
  - Reports of scholarship, deportment and attendance of Hubbard from Phillips Exeter Academy (Box 4, Folder 115)
    - November 27, 1866
    - July 2, 1867
  - List of subjects taken by Hubbard at Rheinischea Friedrich-Wilhelms Universitat at Bonn, Germany, 1883-1886
  - "The Business Side of the Registrar's Office," by J. C. Christensen of Kansas State College, July 8, 1913 (Box 4, Folder 116)
  - "University Business Administration," by J. C. Christensen, January 12, 1912
  - Report of the Class of '68 of the Phillips Exeter Academy by Edward L. Parks, June 1900
  - Field notes relating to Moosehead Lake (Box 4, Folder 117)
  - Description of Natardin or Catardin Mountain, an extract from a letter written by Charles Turner in, 1804
  - Miscellaneous notes about Moosehead Lake, Upper St. John Pond, and "Woods and Lakes of Maine"
  - Notes on East Branch trip (Box 4, Folder 118)
  - Photostat of a journal containing a survey through parts of the country from Penobscot to Quebec, 1764 (Box 4, Folder 119)
  - "The Meaning of 'Merrimac,'" by A. S. Gatshet, October 1898 (Box 4, Folder 120)
  - "Scientific observations on Mount Katahdin"
  - Pamphlet describing the Roach River House, Roach River, Maine
  - Pamphlet describing Mt. Kineo House, Moosehead Lake, Maine (Box 4, Folder 121)
  - Train schedules
    - Maine Central Railroad, July 1, 1889 (Box 4, Folder 122)
    - Bangor and Piscataquis Railroad and June, June 30, 1879
    - 19, 1882
    - Boston and Bangor Steamship Co.-schedule commencing, June 17, 1889
  - Miscellaneous pictures
    - Snapshots of geological rocks (Box 4, Folder 123)
    - Picture of Wilson Pond
    - Sketch of a moose
    - Snapshot of a group of men, taken at Lake Gerald, November 26, 1899
    - A group of etchings, probably scenes in Maine
    - Picture of Henson's "ariel" carriage, 1843
  - Newspaper articles
    - "Geographical Indian Names," by N. T. True, M.D. (Box 4, Folder 124)
    - "Sport at Moosehead Lake"
    - "Indian Names of Kennebec River,", November 20, 1880
    - "The Protections of Fish and Game,", January 25, 1889
    - A letter by John D. Long in which he outlines McKinley's policy
  - "The Indian Names of Boston and their Meaning" by Eben Norton Horsford, November 4, 1885 (Box 4, Folder 125)
  - List of names (unidentified) (Box 4, Folder 126)
  - A resolution of appreciation for Hubbard's services, given upon his retirement from the South Range State Bank, South Range, Michigan, February 14, 1924 (Box 4, Folder 127)
  - Notes about "Two New Geological Cross Sections of Keweenaw Point,", July, 1895 (Box 4, Folder 128)
  - Genealogical notes (brief) about Hubbard's family
- Bound personal and business records
  The bound personal and business records series includes volumes of notes and diaries on the Moosehead Lake region of Maine, letterpress books of professional correspondence, diary, 1893, of activities around Houghton Lake, Michigan, an account book kept while he was a Harvard University student, 1871, and notebooks of class work and research abroad.
  - Diaries, letterpress books, personal account books notebooks, etc., 37 volumes (Box 5)
    (include 1893 diary of activities while in Houghton, Michigan)